Introduction

Every community is the sum of its stories. A tiny fraction of those stories eventually make their way into books, but most live only in the memories of community members.

In 2013, Vancouver Public Library began a project to collect and preserve some of these stories and memories in an online collection that would be available to everyone. At the time, we didn’t anticipate how many different types of memories this project would attract or how profound the demand would be. Stories began to pour in. Some folks came to our offices with photographs or objects that they had been meaning to preserve for decades.

In the following years, library staff equipped with digital recorders ventured out of the library to Indigenous arts festivals, slam poetry haunts, local French-language cafés, and a host of community spaces to map out the cultural life of Vancouver as told by its residents. Over four hundred people shared their unique memories of the unceded Coast Salish territory that has become the city of Vancouver.

Their stories and memories are now available at This Vancouver, an online collection of audio recordings, photographs, and videos clips. The e-book you hold in your hand contains a small sampling of excerpts from this online collection. We hope you enjoy reading these interviews and will continue your journey with us at This Vancouver, where you can hear your neighbours share their stories in their own voices.

Anna Terrana “The Centre Became My Second Home”

Anna Terrana was interviewed on March 1, 2017, as part of the Story City project.

My name is Anna Terrana. Some of the things I’ve done: I’ve been the executive director of the Italian Cultural Centre Society, I was also the president for five years, and I was also a Member of Parliament.

Could you tell me a little about [coming to Canada]?

Well, I was very happy where I was. I’m from Torino, in Piemonte. I used to work with the Americans. I had a very good job, in fact. But I met the man of my dreams, I suppose, and we married. But he was a very unstable person, he wasn’t able to stay in the same place for a long time. And in fact he had just arrived … from Australia where he had lived for nine years. He was originally from Trieste in Italy. And we ended up getting married and he didn’t want to stay in Italy and here we are. Here I am.

We arrived in October 1966. And I was very sad. I didn’t want to be here. I wanted to be where I was … But somehow everything turned in a way that I could not say no. I just had to come. Even at the last minute, I was at the airport, and behind me there was the pilot of the plane, and the woman at the counter said that she could not let me come to Canada because I did not have a visa. I didn’t know I needed a visa, nobody ever told me anything. And so she said, “I cannot let you go.” Then the pilot said, “No, just stop it,” he said, “I’ll take this lady with me to Canada and if they don’t want her, I’ll bring her back.” Well, they wanted me. Here I am.

In ’75, [my husband] and I split, so I found myself alone with this child. Thank God I had a good job. I was the administrator of the BC Place Commissions. I had to look after this child, and I had nobody, no family support, no anything.

I started with Big Brothers, and the United Way, and I went on from there. And then I saw that they wanted to build a centre, the Consul of Italy … They told me “Why don’t you build a centre for the community? And the government will help you.” We started from there.

[I lived in] the same place in Burnaby for, how is it? Forty-six years. So I made up for the eight years that I had to move. Because my husband and I separated, so I stayed there. I stayed there because of David, my son. Because he needed to have some stability in life.

It was very difficult for me to do all the things then. But he was very supportive. He always was there when I needed him. And David, when he was growing up, then we had to run home, make supper, and go again to the meeting, take him to the meeting—poor David. The Centre became my second home. I was thinking of just leaving a bed there because I was there from nine o’clock in the morning ‘till eleven o’clock at night. Weekends, the same thing. People knew that I was there so they came by. They were fun times.

Did you put your son into language school?

David, no. David doesn’t even speak Italian, and you know I used to teach Italian. In Italy, I taught some Italian. And here, I started the ESL courses. The City of Vancouver had this project and again someone gave my name. This was 1969–1970. Peter Davis was in charge of this project from the City of Vancouver and then it involved was also the Federal Government and the United Church. And the idea was to bring, to have a bunch of us … for instance they started with the Italian and Chinese communities. Maggie Ip, you probably heard of her before: she has always been a very active Chinese person and she has also been a counsellor at City Hall. So she was in charge of the Chinese community and I was in charge of the Italian community.

The idea was to bring these people with their children. Because the women ended up staying at home and the men were out working. So they were working and learning English but the women had no chance to do that. So we got them out of the house with their children, and we taught them English. We started in September/October and we ended in June … it was six months altogether. These people in the end could speak English. Because they did have English in their ears and they needed some attention.

We were holding the classes at Saint Francis of Assisi because it was then the Italian church. So downstairs they have a small hall, and we had people looking after the children, and we had grandmothers. But I was teaching in the evening, so no grandmothers because they ended up going in the afternoon, but to this day occasionally I run into to someone and it’s, “Oh Anna!” One in particular, because he lives in Burnaby where I live. But usually I don’t even recognize them because so many years have gone by.

To hear audio clips from Anna’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Introduction

Every community is the sum of its stories. A tiny fraction of those stories eventually make their way into books, but most live only in the memories of community members.

In 2013, Vancouver Public Library began a project to collect and preserve some of these stories and memories in an online collection that would be available to everyone. At the time, we didn’t anticipate how many different types of memories this project would attract or how profound the demand would be. Stories began to pour in. Some folks came to our offices with photographs or objects that they had been meaning to preserve for decades.

In the following years, library staff equipped with digital recorders ventured out of the library to Indigenous arts festivals, slam poetry haunts, local French-language cafés, and a host of community spaces to map out the cultural life of Vancouver as told by its residents. Over four hundred people shared their unique memories of the unceded Coast Salish territory that has become the city of Vancouver.

Their stories and memories are now available at This Vancouver, an online collection of audio recordings, photographs, and videos clips. The e-book you hold in your hand contains a small sampling of excerpts from this online collection. We hope you enjoy reading these interviews and will continue your journey with us at This Vancouver, where you can hear your neighbours share their stories in their own voices.

Inez Cook

“Don’t Panic... We Have Bannock”

Inez Cook was interviewed on July 25, 2017, at The Drum is Calling Festival in Larwill Park. This interview was conducted as part of the Story City project.

Hi, my name is Inez Cook and I am Nuxalk from the Nuxalk Nation from Bella Coola and I was adopted and I grew up in Vancouver. I am the co-founder of Salmon n’ Bannock Bistro. We’re located at 1128 West Broadway. And I was just at The Drum is Calling Festival doing a food demo. And I thought I’d come over and say a little friendly hello.

Well hello, Inez. Can you tell us about your childhood in Vancouver?

Well my childhood in Vancouver, well we kind of lived all over. We started in Burnaby and then Delta, then we moved to Northwest Territory for a couple months and then came back. And we lived in East Van, then we lived downtown. Kinda moved all around the west, lower mainland. Yeah, I grew up here, this is my home. I lived all over the world but it’s always nice to come home. I feel like if I’m away, I miss the ocean.

Can I ask you, what is it that keeps bringing you back, Inez?

Family and the ocean.

There you go. So are you comfortable talking about your relationship to your culture?

Yeah, absolutely. I was adopted out, so I only started really learning about my culture through my restaurant, and I was fortunate enough to get reconnected with my biological family. I went up to Bella Coola and I met five hundred relatives in a three-day potlatch. I received my traditional name, which is Snitsmana, which means ‘the protector of the sacred dance’ and ‘lively.’ I received my button blanket the beginning of my regalia. I’m truly honoured, and now I showcase my heritage with pride.

Tell us how you do that.

Well at Salmon n’ Bannock restaurant on Broadway, all my staff is First Nations we take all indigenous ingredients and serve it with a modern palate, and I’m mentoring people, and I do as much as I can for the community and I’m super proud.

How has it changed your life?

Oh my goodness. I came full circle. I finally felt good in my own skin. That’s how it changed my life. It was epic. I spent my entire life searching for culture, and I’ve always had it within. It’s really special.

Were you raised by a non-indigenous family?

Correct. I was raised in a really good home. I am part of the class action lawsuit, Sixties Scoop, and originally I didn’t want to participate because I was given a good life, but I realized that a lot of people weren’t as fortunate. And at the end of the day, it wasn’t right, it wasn’t the government’s decision to make. And so, therefore I put my name on the class action lawsuit because there are strength in numbers and the stories need to be told. People need to hear about this. It’s really important.

Could you explain what the Sixties Scoop is for people who aren’t aware?

Yeah, absolutely. Well, a little 101 First Nations history is that you know the government set up residential schools across the country, which a lot of people have heard about recently. And you know all the children weren’t allowed to speak their language or learn their culture, grow up with their family. As a matter of fact, my biological mother, she spoke her language fluently, and they poured boiling hot water on her. She got third degree burns and she was hospitalized for three months. When they realized that her family was coming to visit her daily in the hospital, the government went, “Oh no, this is too much family involvement.” So they uprooted her and moved her to another residential school in Alert Bay, away from her family. So what happened is that there’s all these people that are broken. They didn’t grow up knowing how to be a daughter, knowing how to be a mother, knowing how to be a sister, knowing how to be a friend. They didn’t grow up understanding any of that. And then they had children and the government went, “Oh no, we forgot about this part.” Now these ones are having children. So they took us away and adopted us to non-indigenous families. I grew up without my status. I only got my status reinstated as an adult. But I have a biological sister, and she was also adopted into another family, and we also met as adults. So that’s another reason why I put my name on the list, just because I didn’t grow up with my sister. She’s become a great friend. But it wasn’t their right to do that, it wasn’t right.

So your restaurant. How did you start your restaurant?

I have a business partner and we both fly for Air Canada full-time still. We tag team most of the time. So I was in Kelowna during the wine festival. And I saw that there was a Native restaurant there called Kekuli Café, and I came back and I talked to one of my best friends, Remy, and I said, “You know, there is a native restaurant in Kelowna, we don’t have one in Vancouver anymore, the 2010 Olympics are coming here, and we need a Native restaurant in this city and it’s crazy.” And he said, “I’ll work day and night, I’ll make it happen, let’s do it.” So we kind of dove in head first. And now, seven and a half years later, here we are.

And so food is a connection to your culture? And it was before you reconnected with your family?

It was weird because when I saw the sign “Don’t Panic… We Have Bannock” at the Kekuli Café in Kelowna, bannock triggered something. “Oh my goodness I haven’t had bannock since I was a child.” We made it at camp. And I knew that was native bread. And all of a sudden I wanted to learn more, I wanted to know more. Growing up, I didn’t want to know anything about it. I saw drunk people in the ditch up in Northwest Territories—“Who are they? They’re Natives, and I’m not Native.” And that was it, I didn’t want to have any part of it. So it’s really nice to come full circle and to promote and showcase my heritage and be so proud. I was just making a joke at our food demo saying, “First Nations: We’re in.”

To hear audio clips from Inez’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Jeremy Walker

“The Drive Really Looked After Us”

Jeremy Walker was interviewed on July 22, 2017, at The Drum Is Calling Festival at Larwill Park. This interview was conducted as part of the Story City project.

I’m from Kitimat, but kind of raised in Kitimat and Vancouver, both places. I used to come down for the summers all the time. Moved down in ’99. I have a lot of family, I have a huge family here.

So, what area would you go to?

East Van … Commercial Drive, yeah. When all those native housings went up we were the first ones in there. Yeah, it was crazy. There was probably about 150 of us, we were all—100 of us maybe—we were all like twelve to fourteen years old. There was a lot of us, there was a lot of us. We used to travel, we’d walk around, there’d be like thirty or forty of us, all just little kids. We were bad. We were really bad. That’s when all the residential schools was coming out, so we’re the first generation that wasn’t in residential school.

The Drive really looked after us. Joe’s Café used to give us donuts and coffee and hot chocolates all the time. I’m like, “Let’s go see Joe!” whenever we got hungry. He’s like, he’d shake his head, he’d be kind of like, “You guys can’t come keep doing this all the time.” He really liked us, eh? And the bus drivers all watched us grow up, too. The bus drivers used to let us, certain bus drivers, would never get mad. They’d let us on all the time and talk to us. They’re like, “You guys got to calm down,” and stuff. So, it was like, East Van really, they watched out for us. It’s pretty good. Yeah, living on the Drive was so much culture and stuff there, and so much people that want to see us do good.

It used to be really hard for a Native growing up. Like there wasn’t as much opportunity, there wasn’t much anything. But nowadays, the racism, it’s very rare in East Van. Farther you go, you’ll notice it’s a little bit more. Go to Surrey, go to North Van, you know, go past Chilliwack, you know. It’s more stereotyped there. But East Van, there’s so many of us out here and a lot of us are doing really good. A lot of us don’t drink or do drugs anymore, too. People are like “What?” Because we get stereotyped, and they just can’t believe that we don’t drink or do drugs anymore. I’m like “Yeah, it’s been a while.” And there’s a lot of us. There’s a lot of us. Me and my cousins had a show, the Snotty Nose Rez Kids, they had a show, and then we went there and there was about ten of us not drinking. Everybody couldn’t believe it. “Why, you guys aren’t drinking?” The whole table’s like, “Yeah, none of us drink here.” And they were like, from all over the nation because it was the Kanata Fest, they paid for a lot to bring people here. They were paying for their fare and everything, paying for their hotels. This thing’s huge. So they’re all meeting us and we’re meeting all these famous people and they’re like, they can’t believe we’re not drinking. Like, “What’s up with you guys? That’s really cool.” They think we’re really cool. We try, we try to be cool. We try hard.

To hear audio clips from Jeremy’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Andrea Smith

“We Have a Good Hooligan Population Around Here”

Andrea Smith was interviewed on May 10, 2017, at Sidesaddle Bike Shop, the business she co-owns on Commercial Drive. The interview was conducted as part of the Story City project.

As soon as I was old enough, I moved … Well, actually, I went to university first, but the first time I moved out that wasn’t a residence, I moved out to Commercial Drive.

So have you been here since then?

On and off. Yeah, this is my home.

Are there particular aspects to it that makes it feel so much like home?

Well for me at the time, I was like twenty, and I had grown up in the suburbs and I was coming out. Commercial Drive and the West End were the two really identifiable queer neighbourhoods. So I wanted to find community and be out, and this was the place to do it back then.

The Drive was really different then. This was before Craigslist and the Internet. I mean, I’d gotten my first email address like three or four years earlier. So physical spaces were really important in terms of meeting people and making connections and learning how to be gay. And there was this community centre which was above the location where Womyns’ Ware—the sex toy store—still is, called Vancouver Lesbian Connection. And they had a library and, I don’t know, all the things that you have in an old-school women’s centre. And they had a housing board, and I think that’s where a lot of people found roommates. That’s where I found my first gay roommate.

Were there any other places where you remember spending a lot of time hanging out at?

The Drive, generally. I’ve lived here on and off for twenty years. The neighbourhood is dense with memories, pretty much straight up from the water at Powell Street up to— My usual game trail tops out at Trout Lake.

So you’ve been here on and off for about twenty years and have seen quite a bit of change, I imagine?

Yeah, I’ve been through the seven stages of grief with this neighbourhood. I think I kind of probably moved here just at the tail end. I mean, neighbourhoods are always in transition, and I guess depending on which end of the gentrification process you’re on, it can feel like positive change or negative. But when I first moved here it felt like just a miraculous place of a tight-knit community. Basically dykes and Italians in this sort of uneasy truce. Although it seemed like they shared the space really well, because the communities have things in common, too. Like a really strong sense of neighbourliness and a great love of coffee.

And since then it’s really felt like, although it’s taken different forms, it’s been a fairly steady decline in terms of local character. The Drive used to just be a total place for weirdos. And just little changes. It’s so funny. When I moved here, you used to be able to just walk out into the street anywhere on the Drive. You were supposed to look both ways before you crossed the street, but you could just walk out into the street, because the drivers were used to the neighbourhood being so pedestrian-oriented and full of so many empowered weird pedestrians, that they would just drive really carefully. And so the street, even though there were cars on it, it felt very mellow and pedestrian-friendly. And then they put those traffic lights in with pedestrian-controlled signals, probably on paper that makes it safer. But what it did is, it puts in a traffic light and the cars are like, “Green means go, it’s my right of way” and it really changed the character of the street.

And so just as the street has become more developed, I guess, I have felt that those changes have resulted in a loss of a sense of place and connection. And then as the rents go up you lose independent businesses. One of my favourite businesses on the Drive was a fish store that was run by an Italian-Canadian lesbian called Antonia’s School of Fish. That was the place for a business like that back in the day.

I’d asked you about other places that you hung out in the area as well.

Well, one of my favourites is the Skylight Diner. That place is old-school Drive. It hasn’t changed, I think, in the twenty years that I’ve been living here. And the population of people who have been living here for that long, and who are increasingly displaced from the neighbourhood and can’t go to their usual places, that one is just keeping going strong.

Can you describe it a little bit?

It’s just a classic — It’s not a classic greasy spoon like kitschy, it’s like normcore. Noticeable because of its rundown-ness and blandness. It’s like the collected bland aesthetics of the past five decades. It’s got sort of torn up booths and then tables with wood-panelled Arborite, which I think would be the seventies. And then it’s got inspirational posters of dolphins and gardens framed on the walls. So that’s the eighties, I guess. It might top out at the eighties. And they serve Chinese and Canadian cuisine, including a delicious eggs benedict with what appears to be nacho cheese sauce on the top, which is delicious.

But the kids from the high school still go there to get their french fries. And the working class people can still get breakfast out there. I get it, it’s hard to run a business in this neighbourhood that caters to working class people, because you have to charge enough prices to pay your staff to rent homes within commuting distance of your business. And you have to charge enough to pay the rent that this neighbourhood now demands. So it’s kind of a cycle.

I’m sorry. This is a downer. Like I said, I’ve been through the seven stages of grief. Is the final one acceptance?

Were there any queer spaces you can think of from that time period as well?

Well, other than Antonia’s School of Fish, Vancouver Lesbian Connection, which I think might have gone down in ignominy. I mean, feminist and queer politics had shifted and that was kind of a holdover from previous time in some ways. My personal politics, I don’t like to speak ill of former waves of feminism because I’m very grateful for the courage and work that was done by those people. And then times change and movements keep moving forward. But the whole Drive was a queer space. All the breakfast places were staffed by lesbians. I remember there was one very popular local little breakfast spot that was eventually sold. And the first thing the new owner did was fire all the lesbian staff and hire new people. The physical space was still the same but it really changed the character of that place.

There used to be a little movie theatre, the Van East movie theatre, I think, at like Eighth and Commercial. And I think they were a queer film fest venue every year. And they were definitely a hangout. I think they were owned by an Indo-Canadian family but it was a very queer space. But really everything on the Drive. Sophie’s Pet Palace was run by a dyke. There was just a lot of visible dyke business owners, which created a very dykey neighbourhood.

So would you say that is part of the change as well? Do you feel like there’s been a dispersal of that community, or has it just changed and sort of … ?

Well, I think that with the commercialization of public space and the financialization of retail strips, and I mean financialization of real estate generally, but where you see — One of my favourite memories of the Drive was that in the nineties a McDonald’s opened up and a Subway opened up, and they both went out of business because this neighbourhood would not support chains. And it’s not really like that anymore.

I think that queer communities generally are changing because the Internet has made it much easier to find community and find your particular subsection of a community instead of needing to go and live in the gay village. Also, this neighbourhood’s expensive now, and lesbians are women and we make seventy cents on the dollar. And a lot of women are choosing to move out to the suburbs or outlying areas because that’s where they can afford to start a family.

So I’d say the neighbourhood has been watered down. It’s still the same population that’s here. Like you walk up the street and see a lot of the same people that you know. But I don’t know, the vibe is just different.

Do you have other memories of the Drive you’d like to talk about?

It’s kind of hard, my whole life has been here. My memories of my life are largely of the Drive. I mean, when I think of quintessential Drive memories, a lot of time spent in parks with my dog, off leash. A lot of awesome interactions with neighbours. There’s a lawless quality to this neighbourhood that I think the people who live here really enjoy.

I remember one time I was walking my dog, off leash, because she was never on leash, and the Dog Police pulled up, the City Enforcement people, they pulled up and were like, “You need to put that dog on a leash,” and I was like, “I don’t have one,” because I never needed one, and someone yelled from up the block, “Maggie’s Mom!”—because they didn’t know my name, just the dog’s name—“Do you need a leash?” And the enforcement guy was like, I don’t belong here, I’m outnumbered, he was like, “Just get a leash,” and he drove away.

I feel like, I don’t know, the Drive, we kind of look out for each other and a lot of the normal rules that make life boring, it’s not applied here. Whether that’s like no jaywalking or put your dog on a leash.

I have this memory, Halloween on the Drive is always really fun. I remember outside the old Café Roma that isn’t there anymore, I remember one night, Halloween, there was just this mob of Italian dudes letting off fireworks, and I guess somebody called the cops, and then so the cops showed up and the Italian dudes just started showering the cop cars with fireworks. That was pretty awesome. That was a very quintessential Drive moment.

I don’t know, every year there’s so many [moments]. Italians have historically dominated this neighbourhood, but for a while there was that little Brazilian café with a really awesome Brazilian community, and so that just amped up the soccer World Cup insanity.

I know some people find it annoying when there’s hooligans in the street, but I enjoy it. Makes me feel alive. So we have, yeah, a good hooligan population around here.

Any last words? You can talk about Vancouver in general, as well.

I just really, really hope, I mean right now what’s happening with real estate and housing is a global problem. There’s too much money sloshing around the world looking for safe places to be stashed and people who have it are wanting to start putting it in houses and I just really hope that we get some government, any government, with the political will to stem the tide of money that is distorting our housing market. It’s tearing our communities apart and I think it will actually really harm social cohesion in our society because it’s contributing so much to inequality.

If you’re a lottery ticket winner who happens to hold the deed to some shitty eastbound house, you won the lottery over your neighbour who happens to rent and I think it’s a real shame. So I am watching people starting to leave Vancouver. I’ve been waiting for everyone to move to New Westminster for a long time and turn that into Vancouver’s Brooklyn. The queer community is still relevant to me, and I still want to live in a queer community, and I don’t know where it’s going to be when we get priced out of the city, which seems like only a matter of time. Those are my thoughts I guess. I’m hoping for a change, but we’ll see.

To hear audio clips from Andrea’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Julia Lane

“People See You When You’re Flustered

Julia Lane was interviewed on August 4, 2017, at Mount Pleasant Community Centre, as part of the Story City project.

I came into the library. I had my stroller, I had like way too much stuff with me, as I usually do. So I had too much stuff, and I had a library fine, which never happens because I’m very fastidious about not having library fines. I was flustered, and I was wanting to pay my library fine. It wasn’t a lot of money, it was like $2, but I didn’t have any cash, I was trying to find cash, couldn’t find any cash. “So can I just pay you this with my debit card? I know it’s dumb, it’s only $2.” The librarian would say, “It’s okay, settle down, you’re fine.” And then some person came up behind me and he was like, “I’ll pay it for you, it’s fine,” and I was like, “No, no, I can pay it. It’s not like I don’t have the money.” He’s like, “No, you look like you’re having a rough day.” I said, “I’m actually fine, I’m not upset. I just have too many things and I’m flustered.” And so he paid the library fine for me after much protestation on my part, and he gave my son Felix five bucks, and I was like, “We really don’t need to take your money, sir. Like thank you, we’re fine.” And he was like, “No, no, I want him to have it, it’s his now.” That was an interesting moment where I was like, Wow, I must have come off very needy in this particular instance. But I just left feeling very like supported by the community here, feeling like, okay people see you when you’re flustered and might want to help out, so that was really nice.

To hear audio clips from Julia’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Grace Eiko Thomson

“Education Is the Only Solution”

The Story City team was invited to Tonari Gumi, the Japanese Community Volunteers Association, to interview community members. We heard from a range of people speaking about their experience as Japanese-Canadians, their personal histories, and what Tonari Gumi means to them. Grace Eiko was interviewed at the same time as Judy Hanazawa, (the next interview in this book).

My name is Grace Eiko Thomson. I’m a retired person, of course, and a senior, and I was a child when we were interned, and I used to be —I’m sorry, I’m making a mess. But I’m a historian and curator. I began as curator of art exhibitions, and then I’ve been working with the Japanese Canadian National Museum. I was the first Director Curator.

I was going to ask whether you can start with your family’s journey to Vancouver perhaps.

I was born in Steveston Japanese Fisherman’s Hospital in Steveston. Many children in those days went to that hospital because that was the first Japanese-Canadian hospital. In fact, it was very interesting that in Steveston, in producing this hospital, I would say that it was probably one of the first—or the first—Medicare or Canada’s … the Medicare that we have today. They already had it within that community, and that hospital, the members paid six dollars or whatever a year to be a member. But the hospital is open to everyone, anyone who want it. They had a plaque ceremony a few years ago, and I went to it and I was very surprised to see that not just Japanese-Canadians, but other residents of Steveston, were born there or had received service from that. Steveston is a very important part of Japanese-Canadian history. Of course, because that’s where the fisherman first came. The immigrants from Japan came as fisherman there, including my uncles.

My father didn’t come until he was nineteen years old, after he had finished school. He came around 1921 or so, but he was told by his brothers not to get into fish, but to go and learn English. So as a result of that, he kind of travelled across all the way to Winnipeg, worked on the railway lines, and worked in the CPR hotels learning English. And then several years later, he went back to Japan and his parents had arranged for his marriage. So my mother came in 1930. And my father was told not to fish, but to learn English.

In the 1930s he got a job in Vancouver in what is called Codfish Cooperative, which was a cooperative that included Aboriginal, Japanese-Canadians, and Caucasians. So that’s where he was working, and in 1942 we were told that we had to leave our homes. We were living on Alexander Street in Vancouver.

So, I was seven years old, I was going to Strathcona School, and because my mother was expecting her last child, which was her fifth child, we decided to move to Steveston where my uncle was living, and my uncle’s family was in Japan at that time, so he was living alone. So, he said, “Why don’t you come and move with me?” So, we moved to Steveston because Steveston has the Fisherman’s Hospital. So my younger sister was also born there. Then the Steveston fisherman were all pretty well-to-do, they’re well-established. So, they decided to go to a self-supporting place rather than the usual internment sites.

So we went to a place called Ninto Mines, which was a lost gold-mine town, and so we spent the next few years there until 1944 or so, ’44 or ’45, just when the war ended. We were told that we couldn’t go back to our homes in Vancouver. In any event, the government had sold all our properties. Soon after the internment, we moved [to internment camps] around April of 1942, by January 1943 they were already starting to sell our properties. We had nothing to go back to. And then we were told to go east of the Rockies or go to Japan.

My family decided that we would go to Manitoba because my father had been on the railway line, and knew that area, but we weren’t allowed to go into the city, so we were living in a couple of farm villages in Manitoba before we received notice of freedom of movement in 1949–50. So in 1950 we moved to Winnipeg.

That’s the internment years, and I would say that as someone whose life was totally changed, I never really had a normal life because we were always moving, plus my mother could not speak English. So I was interpreting for her from the time I was little, and my father took a job wherever he could get. So, often, very often he was not living with us. He was coming home every second weekend. My brothers, too. My younger brothers were raised without proper guidance of a father, and the mother who couldn’t speak English. The responsibility for me was to look after my brothers. We would go to school together, and if there was a meeting with a teacher, I was the one who went to the meetings even though I was a kid.

My life was totally dictated by the events of my life, and I didn’t go to university until I was married because before that, in the fifties, my parents were settling, and the first jobs I was getting was—I had trained myself to be a stenographer in order to help pay for the mortgage. I started going to university after I was married, and then I focused not on making money or having a good job so much as dealing with my own identity issues. I took courses like Asian art history in order to know about what my cultural background is, and western cultures. I studied those things, and so eventually I became a curator and a historian, and then when I moved to Vancouver twenty-two years ago, and I came to the Burnaby Art Gallery as a curator. The Burnaby Art Gallery was taken over by the city, so I quit because I don’t like a bureaucratic job.

So, what happened then is the Japanese Canadian National Museum was being put together, and they asked me to be a consultant. I worked for almost a year as a volunteer consultant, then they hired me as their first Director Curator, because in order to apply for money, you had to have a position. During that period I totally focused on our history, and really got to understand it. So I would say that my whole life was dictated by the politics of our time, and I’m now eighty-three years old, and I have two sons, and five grandchildren. I’m very blessed, and I have no regrets now, but for many years I was very angry. So, I’m very lucky that I’m in good health, and also that I have resolved things within myself.

I heard during one of the reconciliation events a couple of years ago, the sort of second-generation effects of traumatic events like the Holocaust, like internment. Do you feel like you’ve seen those kinds of effects in the later generations of the Japanese community? Did you actually see what happened?

Well, it’s not so much repercussions as Canada is still not able to get over racist attitudes, and there’s still a large segment of our communities that don’t want to accept outsiders, even though the outsiders are the ones who are making Canada. Even before I was born, in 1907 there was a White Canada Only demonstration in Vancouver, where they came and smashed windows and things. And then of course our internment, too. They called us security risks, but it had nothing to do with security risks. Before the war, we didn’t even have the right to vote, and my parents were naturalized Canadians. I don’t know what that means—we were born in Canada. But in the United States, if you were born in the United States, you automatically became, according to the constitution, you become a full citizen. In Canada, that wasn’t the case. Even if you were born here, you never became citizens. So for that reason like in 1942 when we were interned, under the Geneva Convention you can’t intern. Internment is only for aliens. But then we didn’t have the right to vote, even though we were called naturalized Canadians. So that meant that if that the government evoked the War Measures Act, which allowed them to act through Cabinet, not Parliament, to put out orders for our internment and all that.

So, in a way what happened to us is that the Government of Canada, they labelled us enemy aliens, which meant that we were aliens. But they didn’t call it internment, they called evacuation, like we were saved. But we know that we weren’t treated as full citizens, so we feel it’s justified to say we were interned.

And even today, for instance, with refugees coming and all that, there are a lot of people—I don’t know why they think they own this country when in fact it was taken over by displacing the First Nations people—and they think they have a right to this place, that it is White Canada Only, that attitude still remains.

It’s kind of sad. So, the 150th Anniversary, at least we had Truth and Reconciliation. Canadians are getting to know what happened to the Aboriginal communities, and I think that is a wonderful thing that we are slowly starting. At the same time, on the other hand, we still have a lot of racist attitudes. Things haven’t changed that much, in my opinion. But I did work with Chief Robert Joseph on his Reconciliation Canada project, and it was really a wonderful experience for me. A horrible experience learning about what happened to them, but for me I realized that —well, even throughout my career in working with the Inuit in the Northwest Territories, and then the Cree in Saskatchewan, I’ve worked with those communities—and realized that Japanese-Canadians are not the only ones who have been maltreated, and that helps you to resolve what you think was the worst thing that could happen.

I could equate that in the last few months. I’ve been having terrible back pains. I pulled my back, and I think to myself, “Is that all that’s wrong with me?” I look around and there’s so many people having so many other horrible problems. So, you can’t kind of always think about how terrible things are for you. There’s much worse things going on around you. For me, meeting Chief Robert Joseph and taking part of Reconciliation Canada was a really good experience for me. I’m currently doing a lot of work in community work. Volunteer work.

Just to bring this back to when you first returned to Vancouver. What made that decision for you?

I returned to Vancouver only twenty-two years ago, and that decision was because my parents had moved back here in the sixties, and my mother had lost two of her children, and as well her husband, and she was alone. So I came back here. My younger brother was still living, but even there my mother lost three of her children before she died. So I came back mainly because my mother was alone.

My parents moved back here in 1961, and in her memoir she writes that when they came, because they came up by train in those days, she said when she saw the mountains and everything, she said she had feelings of nostalgia returning to this place where they had started their marriage, their family life. She says this. But for me, I can’t say that I felt that at all, because Winnipeg had been my whole life, and coming back here probably made me face my own history much more closely than if I had remained in Winnipeg. Because Winnipeg at that time, when I was growing up, we were probably the first Asian people that a lot of people saw. There were Chinese restaurants and things, but there weren’t Chinese people or Japanese people walking the streets. So you kind of assimilated into the community.

But when you come here, you really feel the Asian presence, and also the presence, still, of racism. Racism is something that you can’t erase totally. There’s always somebody there who’s going to make some comment. Even my children, who are mixed, when they were little, I could tell from the people in our neighbourhood that they saw my children as having a different mother. So they’re looked upon differently from other children. That’s the first time I realized that my intermarrying didn’t do anything in terms of getting rid of that aspect.

So when you returned to Vancouver, was there a particular neighbourhood that you returned to?

No, that’s another thing. Japanese-Canadians were told to go east of the Rockies, they called it a dispersal policy, and that meant that we were told that we should not be clustered because we are causing racism by living clustered. That’s what Prime Minister Mackenzie King said, and so we were careful not to live in the same neighbourhood. So when I came back to Vancouver, of course, the area where the Japanese-Canadians used to live in the Powell Street area, that had totally turned into a slum area, and it’s reviving now. But even so, today there’s the gentrification that’s going on. The developers moving in, and the people who are living there now are getting displaced. So that area has terrible history of displacement.

Can you talk about the City apology?

The City apologized, but at the same time: What’s “apology?” For me, City or the Province or the Canadian government apologizing without really doing something tangible, you know? I really think that education is a major thing that they failed on. Even if we get an apology, they don’t say, “Well, we’re going to make sure this doesn’t happen again, and it will be in the education system.”

Seventy-five years later, it’s not in the school curriculum properly. It’s supposed to be in the curriculum, but it’s up to the teachers. So the teachers have to learn this. If the government doesn’t provide it in textbooks or whatever form, then the teachers are not going to take that time and energy to produce programs to teach it, because it’s not up to them. It’s on the curriculum, but it’s up to the teachers, how or when you produce it.

So, it’s very individual based on the teacher’s willingness to do the education? So, you didn’t go back to …

No, I didn’t go back. No, no. I was renting because I was working at the Burnaby Art Gallery. When I first moved, I moved with a friend. So we just chose anywhere. But I also lived in North Vancouver for a while and came over the Second Narrows Bridge to go to Burnaby Art Gallery to work. But finally, I live on Cambie and Sixteenth now. I chose that area. My son was saying, “If you’re not coming back to Winnipeg, then you should live somewhere where you can grow old without worrying about transportation and things.” So we chose that, and it’s been a good choice.

It has nothing to do with our history because the area I had spent my first seven years in Vancouver is not an area that Japanese-Canadians moved back to. Because as I said, it used to be a thriving community. It had everything. My mother didn’t even have to learn English. All the streets were full of shops and everything. And that was totally destroyed. So there was no reason to come back, but our community has the annual Powell Street Festival to remember this, and also a lot of our community, young people, are now working with Downtown East Side groups to try to help with dealing with issues like displacements and the gentrification that is making it practically impossible for people living there as the rent goes up. And I’m troubled with rent going up. It doesn’t mean that the provincial government is going to raise their benefits.

At this moment, Vancouver east side is going through terrible issues that have to be resolved, and I don’t know how they can resolve it. But I’m really, really grateful, and happy that our younger generation within the Chinese community as well as the Japanese community are working in that community, helping. For me that didn’t happen ten years ago. Everybody tried to forget the past. And now there’s much more attention paid to it. Because if you understand your past, then you can do something in the present, because you don’t want that to happen again. But if you don’t know anything about your past, you don’t do anything.

So I think that things are changing, but the overall Vancouver situation, I don’t think is getting better.

Are there any last words that you’d like to tell?

I think, for me, my end is getting near, and I’m still trying to write a bit of a memoir to leave behind, because my mother left me one. So the main thing is: Act according to your heart, according to who you are. But also that I would really like to push education. To me, education is the only solution, in my opinion, and I think many of our community members know this, and they’re working on it. We have really good people like Laura working on it, and Judy [Hanazawa] is the Human Rights Committee person. She’s chair of our main organization. So I feel very good that there are many people involved right now.

To hear audio clips from Grace’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Judy Hanazawa

“Vancouver Needs to Learn as We Go”

The Story City team was invited to Tonari Gumi, the Japanese Community Volunteers Association, to interview community members. We heard from a range of people speaking about their experience as Japanese-Canadians, their personal histories, and what Tonari Gumi means to them. Judy was interviewed at the same time as Grace Eiko Thomson, (the previous interview in this book).

My mother went back to Japan during the thirties as a young child and returned again when she was fifteen, and she and my father just got married at the point where Pearl Harbor happened. Everybody was living in Steveston, and they just married, and my sister was born in ’41 and then everybody had to go through the internment.

As Grace had mentioned, there were many Japanese-Canadian fishing families who were able to get into the self-supporting camps, which is what happened with my family. So they ended up in Bridge River, which is near Lillooet, that area—my grandparents, my mother and father, and my sister, who was already born in Steveston, and then my middle sister was actually born in Bridge River.

The difference in her life—being a premature, very tiny, tiny baby—and my mother’s hardship, I think indicated how tough life was in Bridge River. Eventually my father found work in a sawmill in Merritt, so my family and a few other Japanese-Canadian families moved to Merritt, which is where I was born.

The connection to Vancouver is that rather than go right back to Steveston post-war, my father was able to get back into fishing by 1950 because all the Japanese-Canadians were able to return in 1949, back to the coast. Many families didn’t, but my family I think had a very attached attitude about ocean and fishing and their livelihood, so everybody returned to fishing, and my father did in 1950. But they decided to move into Downtown Eastside Vancouver, Strathcona. And it’s true what Grace has said about families not returning and the community in that area of Vancouver being decimated, because there was no more Powell Street corridor of Japanese shops in the town there.

But there was still the Japanese language school, there was still the Vancouver Buddhist Temple, and so my parents felt that there was the beginning of a tiny community to begin growing. I went to Strathcona elementary school, post-war, as my sisters did as well, and I grew up in Eastside Vancouver in Strathcona until I was fifteen years old.

And I just totally thought that the kind of life there for a child growing up was normal, which it was, and yet what was so wonderful about Strathcona, in that era of post-war Vancouver, was that there was all kinds of children of all kinds of ethnic backgrounds. Including the African-Canadians families in the Hogan’s Alley area.

It was a time when we all knew we were from culturally different backgrounds, but somehow we were all Strath kids, and we were all Eastside kids, and I think the friendships that were made there are lasting to this day. So of course I’ve got my Strathcona friends, and so do my sisters, and there’s a lot of crossover, even though the Chinese-Canadian community and Japanese-Canadian community were not connected really, and Chinese-Canadians really had issues about Japan because of what happened in China. So grandparents had these attitudes, and yet us kids at Strathcona totally mingled and there were marriages later, there were couples going steady, it was quite a mixed, wonderful kind of little growing-up environment for us kids.

Strathcona was interesting, too, because many of the teachers were British—Anglo-Saxon—and so they had this kind of British attitude about things, too, and yet they were trying to create us into little sort of British-attitude kids, stiff upper lip and so on. It was kind of a strange mix.

In the middle of that there was a Jewish music teacher, Mr. Goldberg, who was wonderful, and he created his own operas, and we all had operas every second year at Strathcona. It was wonderful.

But anyway, at the point where everybody else went to Britannia High School in Eastside Vancouver, the expropriation of properties in Vancouver happened in the ‘60s and so the pressure was on to sell property to bring in the freeway entrance which was the plan at the time. And that’s why Hogan’s Alley disappeared, too.

So at that point, my parents sold because there was pressure to sell to the city, and we moved to South Vancouver, which was a completely different life for me, I was the one who went through high school at Killarney High School. And it was a sea of white faces, and for the first time I knew what it was to be a minority, to feel the sort of veiled racism quite a lot, and realize that Strathcona was very special.

I did graduate from Killarney, I went to UBC, I became a social worker later. I married, you’ll find that in the third generation of our Japanese Canadian community, there was totally majority of outmarriage. My husband was Caucasian, a music teacher. It was an interesting life. We had two children, he’s passed away now, but sometimes I think he had issues with his own stability.

But as I graduated from university, I became a social worker; he was a music teacher. We went up north, our children were born in Hundred Mile. Our marriage didn’t work out, and I came back to Vancouver eventually.

At the point of Japanese-Canadians getting Redress, I was able to get money because of being in that age group which was affected by the internment. So with my own $21,000, I went back to school and got a Master’s of Social Work, and became a single parent raising my children.

Also it connected me to the Squamish Nation, where I continue to have ties to this day, and that’s where I basically learned what it was to work in your community, and to look to supporting your own community. I learned so much from my ties to the Nation, and all the strong women, mostly, who I worked with there. And also I became quite sensitized to aboriginal issues and aboriginal rights, and the unresolved issues for their community.

At that point of my marriage, me single parenting, I finished my university and then I ended up working in the Vancouver area. I even worked in Strathcona as a social worker again. It was interesting to do that. And it was also very, very challenging because of the unresolved issues with aboriginal women, Downtown Eastside Vancouver, and the struggles of poverty. All those things became very much an awareness of the ongoing struggles of so many communities.

This was in the nineties, in the nineties, it was very difficult. However, I also became quite involved in my own community being inspired by working at Squamish Nation, and receiving my Redress money. And so I did become involved in human rights issues and social justice issues in my own community.

And that this point now, my children are grown, I’m a grandparent. And again, it’s interesting how our own Japanese-Canadian community has gone through various changes. It’s very clear that most of my generation, my third generation, outmarried. And so we have many children who I think were driven by their own need for identity to come back to know more about their Japanese-Canadian roots.

It’s certainly affected a lot of the young people that we work with now, who are, as Grace said, they’re working in the Downtown Eastside. Understanding that their great grandparents were there as well, and understanding what displacement is. The great work they’re doing is in partnering with the residents of the Downtown Eastside.

The blending of our history with the current issues of the day, and making sure that it’s relevant by standing with people who are facing displacement. It’s a very great concern that we have in the human rights area of our community, tied in with the young leaders who are doing the work, right in the area.

I agree with Grace that I see a lot of positive change and yet, it’s just seeing how the waves of generations have come through. For sure Vancouver, I think, needs to learn as we go, too. We’ve gone to city council about the Downtown Eastside issues. We’ve wanted to say to council “As you apologize to Japanese-Canadians about displacement in the forties, you cannot ignore displacement going on in that very area where many Japanese-Canadians lived.”

And so we’re going to be holding the city to making sure about that, so our role is in backing up and standing with the people of the area. At this point now, it’s just a matter of more work in that area, and seeing as Grace said, that we need to stand with the First Nations as well, and I completely feel that way, too, because of my ability to work in the community at Squamish Nation. It’s been quite an eye-opening experience.

There’s such a great acceptance of humanity that First Nations people hold. Their first tendency is to show respect, and give respect. And it’s incredible to me, with what has happened in their community, that they still hold to those principles no matter what. And it’s been very gratifying for me to be able to work there.

Can you talk a little bit about how you first got involved in the Squamish nation?

Yeah, I went back to UBC because of the Redress payment I received and I was able to go into the Masters of Social Work program. And my practicum placement—

One of the issues I was aware of from being a social worker without a degree—I had a B.A. and I worked for the province—was the high number of aboriginal children in care. One child that I had worked with had attempted suicide because he was adopted by non-First Nations people, and they had a marriage breakdown and had issues of their own, and they actually brought him back to the Ministry to say, “We cannot, our marriage is breaking down, we cannot continue to look after him.” And he was fifteen years old, and he became a child on my caseload after he attempted suicide. And so some of our work was to try to reconnect him back to his nation.

So being aware of that, and aware that First Nations were beginning to do their own child welfare work, I went into getting my degree and got placed at Squamish Nation with that kind of focus of saying, “If you’d like me to help in this area, I’m available.” Which is exactly what we did. We developed the Nation’s own agency in the Nation, and we still had to use the provincial law, but it was on the terms of applying it within their own community, using culture and values of the people.

And it’s still evolving in that way now. So that was how I got connected there. And then regarding Vancouver, I live in Eastside Vancouver, I still feel very strong ties to Strathcona.

It’s interesting, like I said, I feel the ties to the Downtown Eastside and the language school, it does hold Japanese-Canadians together, there still, because of the Buddhist temple at the corner of Jackson and Powell. And the language school which also has community events on Alexander. So there are gatherings in the area, for sure.

There are some gathering places, but I do agree with Grace, it’s nowhere near what it was. There is not the community that there was before. I think it’s helped to have the post-Redress funding towards to different organizations who gather people, like Tonari Gumi, they gather there, and a lot of seniors still go there. And that’s a good thing.

The Japanese language school has a community hall connected, as well. So those are places for gathering and there have been large events there.

Did you go to the language school?

I did. That was the fairly common thing with us Japanese-Canadian kids in post-war Eastside Vancouver. We often went to the language school three days a week, after English school. So it wasn’t unusual to go Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday morning to Japanese school. When you went Monday to Friday to Strathcona for regular school, yeah, I did go.

And your children, did you decide to put them in language school as well?

I tried for a bit, but we were living out in the Fraser Valley. There was a woman who wanted to start a Japanese school, and she tried for the one month and then she gave up. We even had some lessons right in my house, but yeah, they don’t have the language. And my own language, my mom passed away in 2006, so she was the one person I used to speak to. So the language, it’s one of the major things that is a very concrete thing, if you look at our community, and the effects of interment, and of racism. And what Grace is saying is very true, it’s always been an issue. And we’re going to have an intergenerational gathering, I think at the end of this year, and the matter of what everybody went through, the racism in their life experience, is very concrete for everybody. So it’s not something that somebody can say, “Well, we’ve outgrown that,” or, “We’ve evolved.” No, it’s still very much there, and you always have to address it and be proactive about it. It’s always there to be proactive about, it’s always there.

And in this era, too, we were just talking [about] what happened at the anti-racism march in March when the Sons of Odin appeared and threw smoke bombs at the people.

So those things are happening as well, and so I think it’s always an issue. And for my children, it’s an issue as well. Because they’re biracial, the thing for them to get asked is, “What are you?” The thing for me to have gotten asked was, “So where’s your family from?” You know? Because there’s an assumption you’re a perpetual foreigner.

I’m always nice, so I say, “Well, I’m Japanese-Canadian,” so they know, but the fact that I’m a third generation wouldn’t have occurred to anybody, because people make assumptions because of your appearance. You were born somewhere else and you’re here as an immigrant.

Did any of the grandkids go into the language schools yet? Are they still young?

Yeah, my granddaughter actually did go to the language school. It was an interesting experience because more of the kids who go to language school speak Japanese at home. And there are quite a number of Japanese-born women who’ve married Canadian husbands, and so there’s biracial children who’ve spoken Japanese at home because of their moms, and who’ve gone on to language school.

And my granddaughter didn’t have that. So she’s in French immersion now, but it was kind of difficult for her, and so my daughter decided in the end to focus on her getting involved in other things and then she went on to French. She’s nine now.

It is very much a language loss. Even though I went to Japanese school and I spoke Japanese with my mother, my language is very not there. Grace is really lucky, she’s good at language, Japanese speaking. Her mom taught her at home, and she retained it.

So she’s a phenomenon because there are many people who are even Grace’s age who don’t speak Japanese very much at all. And so the manner of what happens to a community with issues like internment and so on, one very concrete loss is language. Huge loss, because language does retain culture embedded in it.

In some ways, there was a desire not to be hated, not to be the enemy alien. And so there was almost a decision with some families to not teach their children. But, you know, that’s a direct result of the historic situation for our community and social attitudes like racism, but still, that systemic racism decided upon what happened with our community and so one of the losses that is very concrete to me is the loss of the language. And culture. And as you become, you’re here, you do evolve as Canadian with the generations, but with the freedom to evolve in your own way, but with our community that freedom was taken, right? So it’s just abrupt. You can see the abruptness in this third generation of what happened. Yeah. So. Anyway. [laughs] It’s so heavy duty. But this is Vancouver’s story, too.

To hear audio clips from Grace’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Sophia Karasouli-Milobar

“Where Is a Greek Church?”

Sophia Karasouli-Milobar was interviewed on January 26, 2017, as part of the Hellenic Stories project.

I came to Canada in 1990. I’m a different type of immigrant. I was not a refugee, or an economic immigrant. I came because I met my husband while we were both studying in England and we fell in love. He was Canadian, and we decided to come here. So in a way, it was much easier for me coming here. In that sense, I came here with a Canadian who knew the system, had family. I knew English, because I was a Master’s degree student in England. So I didn’t have any difficulties, really, with the language, and still it was very difficult.

I remember the very first thing I did was to ask around: “Where is a Greek church? Where is a Greek community?” I felt I was so far away from my country, and from my own family, and my parents, and everybody else. And somehow the distance, the long flight, made me realise how far I am and how difficult it will be to visit. When I was in England I could really get back home much easier.

Anyway, so they told me about the community, and I came here. I think it was the second day I was in Canada, we didn’t even have a place to stay; we’re staying with an aunt of my husband [and] he told me where the Greek community is, and I came and met with the secretary. She was from my part of the world. And we started talking about some people that I knew and she knew, and I felt so much better, right away.

And then she said “You come to the church on Sunday and you will meet more people.” And I was never truly a churchgoer before. I would go on feast days, but I wasn’t a regular Sunday churchgoer. But I went. People really welcomed me after the service. I was introduced by the secretary to some of her friends. And they were so happy to see someone from Greece. Some of them remembered themselves, when they came, and they didn’t know anyone. I had some people who really opened their arms, so to speak, and they welcomed me. They invited me and my husband to their place for dinner. Or there was a picnic that the Greeks would organize, and we would go.

And very soon I started to feel I belong somewhere. And I can hear my language and I can speak my language. And although, as I said, that was not an issue, because I did know English, still I felt at home speaking and hearing Greek being spoken. So anyway, then I started coming to the church on a regular basis. And it was more that, not just the religious aspect, but the social aspect. That was a way of connecting with the community.

To hear audio clips from Sophia’s interview and other Hellenic Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Angelo Pappas

“Greeks Are Citizens of the World”

Angelo Pappas was interviewed on February 5, 2017, at the Hellenic Community Centre as part of the Hellenic Stories project.

My dad came to Canada in 1910, and he arrived from New York and went straight to Prince George. There were jobs there in those days. There were many Greeks in those days. They came to Canada, especially British Columbia, for work.

And of course they worked in any way they could find a job. But since he knew the language, he later on became foreman when they were building the Grand Tram Railway from Prince Rupert to Prince George, from there all the way to Vancouver. He had more than two hundred people, and he had many native people.

Now this story, it wasn’t given to me from my father. But this story was given to me from an elderly Indian person, here, when I came in 1956, later on. I mean, about ’57, ’58. This old fellow, it was down on Pender Street, and he told me, he said, “Pappas … oh Pappas,” he says. “I had a friend,” he says. Actually he said, “We had a friend, the native people: Pappas, George. And he was from a small village in Greece, and he was foreman when we were building the railroad. And he always cared for the native people and gave us jobs.

“And I was a water boy,” he said. “I was a water boy, and I never forget him.” And he told me all the story. And I went to Smithers, one time, to find out, because it was in the archives there: how it was built, and how people were doing it —handwork, everything.

And I found quite a few things. But I knew further on, the story, from my dad and from my uncle. They were working with the fur industry later on. As they were working in the railways, they were buying furs and selling furs, pelts.

And later on it became a company, what was known here in Vancouver, the Pappas Furs, Western Canada Fur Auction. And that is the company that I worked for. I came right into it.

I travelled throughout the North, the Arctic, everywhere in the Arctic, western Arctic and eastern Arctic, meeting with Eskimos and Inuit and native peoples and white people, working, because I was in the business, in the fur business. But in my capacity, to advise …about the quality of the fur pelts, and that’s why I went there. I wasn’t going just for business, but I was going as an advisor to talk to natives, to people, to see when to take the pelts, when the quality is good, when to trap them, when it is breeding season to avoid it, and how to protect the species. It was something that I was very much interested with.

And this is what made me really tied up to the country, tied up. When you are young, you’re a little bit on these things. You are really enthusiastic, and I was enthusiastic, and I participated in many other committees, in political committees, and everything, because I wanted to be part of what was happening, how this country was built, and how this province was built, and everything.

And it takes us to where we are today. And many years, of course, we had to work, to work for the community, to build up the community. And this story is what brings me, ties me to the country. Not only that my parents were here early, before we were born, or my brother was born here. But it ties me to the development of the country.

We had to find time for the development of the community. The community was built by people who came here in the turn of the nineteenth century, early, on 7th Avenue. It was 2305 West 7th Avenue. That’s where the Hellenic Community was. That’s where the Saint George original cathedral was. Today it’s used by the Kitsilano groups, and they have the homes and everything. But they use that old church as a referral centre for many people.

And lately Father Costantinos, they have a Divine Liturgy once a year, because they want it. They said their community should have a Divine Liturgy once a year, or twice a year. So Father Costantinos was kind enough, because young people are a little bit more spiritual, do those things.

And that keeps the span of the community life, the history of the community together, without [selling] the property, without, “Well, we’re not there anymore. That’s nothing.” But it’s not. The sentimental is there. The sentimental is there: You don’t sell church.

But this property, this is how it’s done here. For instance, in Greece, church is here, from the third century. It just stays there. Nobody can sell it. Nobody can move it, nothing. It stays there. You have been to Greece. You have seen all the churches there, little tiny one churches. But it brings history from the first Christians.

We moved here, and we had to develop the property. More people were coming in the sixties. Actually after the middle of the fifties—’55, ’56—up to the end of the sixties, it was a lot of Greek people were coming. And new families, lots of kids. Greek schools had more than a thousand students in the early seventies. There was four schools, and they had at least three hundred plus, each school.

And of course, those kids grew up. They got married, new generation, everything. Now, of course, it is in a form of the communities, part of the general community. When we opened this community centre, we had to make sure that this community centre wasn’t a sort of community centre for the Greek community. It was a community centre to be used by the neighbours, to be used by the community at large.

We built here in excess of what we were allowed, footage. But we asked the city, “This building will be open to the community.” It’s not only Hellenic. And it was used, and is used, all the time. People to come use for meetings, for this, for seniors, all kinds of people, political gatherings, or whatever.

And this is good because it ties the community to the rest of the community, to be part of what we are. You see, what I believe—and all of us believe, especially, the ones we found here—that we must contribute to the development of the Canadian society. We must be there, like the country is a mosaic. It’s like a dome in those churches in Europe. And that mosaic, by itself is no good, nothing. But all together makes the edifice—that is the important thing.

And we wanted to be part of that. So when English-speaking people or French-speaking people or any other people come to the community here, they feel they’re in their home. They don’t feel that they’re in a private club or something. They feel they are home.

That’s what the Greeks are. They are citizens of the world, really, from the ancient times, keep on traveling, only few, but you must spread it along.

And I would say that we are very happy about it, what we came. And the festivals that is done, the Greek Day that was established at the time we built this community centre was part of that just to open it up. Food festivals and everything in order to collect money, of course, to sustain the society and the buildings itself. But it was with the idea, an open door, an open window to everybody. And it’s worked. It’s worked.

We just hope that the new generation now will do that, will continue that, and I think they will. Because the new generation have more, how can I put it? More to themselves, they are established, they’re educated in this country.

When we came here, we were just plain people, immigrants from the old country. I had the Board of Directors —I was the President, and sometimes, there’s not one who knows English, and I knew not much myself. You know?

But we had to do it. I reached outside. I went to people who were educated, and I said, “I need you.” “Oh, I haven’t got time.” “Yes, but I have to send a letter to the Prime Minister. You want me to write it? And ridicule everybody?” I said, “Or you want to come and help me to write it? I’ll give you my opinion, my ideas, but you write it.” You know?

And many people told me, “Oh, you S.O.B., you know how to get people together.” But it was the truth. That was the truth. That’s how it was. It was the influx of the new Greeks in the fifties and sixties, were the older ones that were born here, for some reason, they were just overshadowed on the side. So what I always wanted to make sure they come in.

In this property, we got $400,000 from the government. And why we got it? Because it was just that. This property, it will be made available to everybody. The city wanted something like that, but it’s the Province who insisted that we want something like that because all community centres, they were not open to people, sort of. But this was open to everybody. So there was program in the federal government in those days, but it was in 1970, ’75. It was a program from the federal government that any project, city or public project, when it belongs to individual societies and made available to the rest of the community, they will contribute part of it.

So we came in, and of course, they contributed, but part of the thing, it was that we are open to everybody. So many times—maybe I bore you with this—people they say, “But Angelo, twenty-five years passed.” Yes, but our commitment hasn’t passed. It will never pass. Twenty-five years it was, that we have to have it open for everybody. But our commitment is to the community at large. And we’re part of the community at large.

I have five grandchildren. They’re not going to be around because they are the community at large, right? And this way, it makes it easy for them. They feel proud to be part of what we are. And I think, in a small way, the Greek community [of] Vancouver contributed a lot to the development of the city. It has a good name, very good name out there, very good name.

We took part with committees in the multicultural societies. We had a committee to be part of the discussion, national discussions on that, on the immigration. We were present in those important negotiations, in the last few years as they take place.

And I think we should be proud about it. And I am. I am, and I think everything’s fine.

To hear audio clips from Angelo’s interview and other Hellenic Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Nikki Roussanidis

“A Community of Really Tight-Knit Families”

Nikki Roussanidis was interviewed on February 1, 2017, as part of the Hellenic Stories project.

My name is Nikki Roussanidis, and my maiden name was Balatsas. My family came to Canada, my mom and dad, came to Canada in 1954. Came into Regina and then moved to Kitimat in 1956, then came back down to Vancouver in 1960 or ’61.

That year, my father opened up his first business in Vancouver, Leo and Chris’ Service Station. It was an establishment, a Texaco station, on the corner of Broadway and Carolina from 1961 to 1984. His brother and himself, Chris Balatsas and Leo Balatsas, opened up a second service station in 1977 on 49th and Victoria Drive. They were prominent businessmen in the Greek community, both of them.

Growing up, it’s all I can remember, as a real youngster, having to go to the Texaco on Broadway to visit my father because he worked literally from sunup to sundown. There were days that we hadn’t seen him for days, and my mother would drive us to the gas station so we could see my dad.

And then later on in life, at twelve years old, it didn’t matter at this point whether I was a boy or a girl. I started working at the gas station pumping gas, as all my friends worked in their parents’ business. A lot of them were lucky, they had restaurants so they were indoors. But I have pumped many tanks of gas in a skirt and shoes.

What else can I tell you? Growing up in Vancouver, it was a really small community of really tight-knit families. People that had immigrated at the same time. A lot of them knew each other from Greece, as my parents knew a lot of people that they grew up together in Greece, in Piraeus, and came here and met again in Vancouver. We were like a small family of families. People are still referred to as Uncle John or Uncle Nick or Aunt Tessie or Thia Georgia because it was so close.

Of course with my uncle’s family, my dad and his brother, we were together dinners, Easter, Christmas, and weekly visits three, four times a week, even though they worked together all day. But everybody I knew worked in their parents’ business, it was a given back then. We didn’t have a choice.

I guess the other good thing about growing up here is when I was a teenager at fourteen, they resurrected the Maids of Athena, which is the girls’ subsidiary of the AHEPA, American Hellenic Educational Progressive Association.

The AHEPA was the men’s association. The Daughters of Penelope was the women’s association. The Sons of Pericles was the teenaged boys’ association. The Maids of Athena was the girls’ association.

The Maids of Athena got resurrected because the chapter always evolved. And then when the girls grew up, they left. Then it dissolved, and then they would resurrect it. When I was fourteen, we resurrected the Maids of Athena with about twenty teenaged girls.

At that time it was in the seventies, so disco was a big hit here. We held a fundraiser down here in the Greek community, in this hall. We had over three hundred, four hundred kids attend at a dollar a ticket. Our chapter made a lot of money that one night. At one dollar a ticket, you can imagine when fifty cents for pop, because we couldn’t have alcohol. We were all underage and we got chaperoned. We gave it all to charity, as I recall. I happened to be the president of the Maids that year, for two years running.

What else can I tell you about the Daughters of Penelope, which everybody wants me to talk about? The Daughters of Penelope in Vancouver has been running strong for a number of years. I’m going to say some time in the fifties. I’m not exactly sure. Mary Leonidasv and Marie Kyriakos and Lili Spilos, Sara Anton, who was the pianist for the church for many, many years, were some of the founding members. My mother, Elizabeth Balatsas, is still a member. She’s eighty-nine years old. The chapter’s still going okay.

And so the society raises money for charities?

The Daughters of Penelope, again, the women’s subsidiary of the AHEPA, raises money for charities. Some of our notable charities, we raised the first $25,000 seed money to start the Hellenic Chair at SFU. Over the years, cancer research, Doctors Without Borders, Covenant House, Food Bank. Most recently, we gave another major donation to BC Children’s Hospital in the amount of $25,000. We gave $10,000 to MS research probably in the last fifteen years. It’s a small group of women now.

Regrettably, the interest has died. The older women are too old to fundraise, and younger women don’t see it as a necessity to come out and bond with other Greek women and do that sort of fundraising, regrettably. The Philoptochos does a lot of that. It’s one of those things, right?

A few of the other people have been talking about where you would hang out and talk with other people or just hang out with other people that you knew in the Greek community.

When we were kids, you mean?

When you were kids, yeah.

Oh, God, Bino’s. Everybody went to Bino’s on Broadway and Arbutus.

What was Bino’s?

It was just a coffee place. Bino’s was a chain of all night long —it’s like a Denny’s, let’s put it that way. We’d go to Bino’s. There was a place called Tuesday’s on Broadway. All the Greek kids would hang out there. It was a given, Sunday night everybody went to Tuesday’s for coffee.

After the clubs, everybody went to Bino’s or Denny’s for breakfast. We had the GOYA here for a while, so Father Partsafas office has the GOYA going in the Community Centre. The GOYA, when I was a part of it, we actually did some traveling down to the States and met other chapters from Seattle. When I was part of the Maids of Athena, again, we brought the chapters from Seattle and Portland. I can’t remember what other —Spokane, possibly. We had sleepovers and we went back and forth. It was a very, very simple childhood.

The Greek community was sort of like the hub for us. Our parents, if we told them we were coming here for an event, they never batted an eye. Everybody met here for one thing or another. They started—I don’t know—some sports activities. I don’t remember. We had volleyball going. Too far back to remember.

Was that mostly at this current location?

This current location. Yeah. That’s why they built it. My father was on the board here for many, many, many, many years. Again, Wednesday night was a meeting, Monday night was a meeting, this was a meeting, that was a meeting. The immigrants that came here really strived to build this community centre for their kids and their grandkids. All of it was volunteer back then. I don’t think there were any paid positions other than the secretary of the community, I think. The priest, obviously, but the man has to live.

To hear audio clips from Nikki’s interview and other Hellenic Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Effie Karapidakis

“Which Is Your Homeland: Greece, Crete, or Canada?”

Euthalia (Effie) Karapidakis was interviewed on February 5, 2017, as part of the Hellenic Stories project. The original interview was conducted in Greek, and transcribed and translated at Vancouver Public Library.

My name is Euthalia Karapidakis, and I have been in Vancouver since 1964. I came here engaged, my fiancé having been here before me, in order to get married. We got married at Saint George’s church, at Seventh and Vine. And we baptized our children there. Later on, I got pregnant. I have two children, two sons. As things turned out, one of them lives in Greece right now, in the place I came from. I was born in Heraklion, Crete. That’s where I came from. And my child lives there now, in the same house I grew up, my son with his wife and their two daughters. We have been going back to Greece, we kept visiting to Greece all these years.

We kept special ties with our homeland all these years, and that’s why my children loved Greece, although they were not born there. We had that longing of returning to the homeland and we tried twice to go and settle back there. We sold everything here, we put our belongings to containers and returned to Greece. Our children grew up, they finished high school, and one after the other—they are three years apart—went to University in Greece, again having in mind that they will settle and stay there. We kept visiting Greece every year since our children were here and we still do, until last year when we got a small apartment near our children. We hope, now that we are both pensioners, that we will go and spend our last years there. Last summer, last year that I was in Greece close to my children for three months, my son often asked me a question, which I would like to repeat here. He was asking: “Which is your homeland: Greece, Crete, or Canada?” However, when I am in Greece, the first two-three months I am OK. It is summer, summer vacations. When we stay longer, I start to miss Vancouver, our friends. We have been here for so many years, almost fifty-two. So many years, I have made so many friends that I can easily say—in my mind and my heart—they can even replace my family.

How was Vancouver when you first came here?

When I first came here, I liked it. I am a person who likes the company of people. When I came here, I looked for opportunities to get involved in the community. I tried to help at the old church—of course, it was not very organized in the old days. I lived in the area of Main Street. We lived there the first years. We rented only for one year when I first came, Main and Twenty-Sixth. Then we bought a house on Main and Thirtieth. We lived there for many years. Then we bought a house near Oakridge Centre. We stayed there until 1992 when we moved to Richmond. The last nine years I have been a board member of the Hellenic Community of Saint George’s, and the last six years I have been a Treasurer of the Community

Have you served in the Philoptochos all these years?

I am a member of the Philoptochos all these years. I was a board member for twenty-five years. For six or eight years—I can’t remember exactly—as President of the Philoptochos. Also, I was quite involved in the Cretan Association, one of the largest associations that was ever formed in Vancouver. It has quite a few members, more members than any other [Greek] association. Of course, now the associations have started to become scarce; now they leave, they almost get dissolved, because the young people do not have the same needs that we had when we first came here. We missed our homeland so much, we had come to a foreign land for the first time. I was also a board member [of the Cretan Association]. President of the Cretan Association. Together with my husband, my children, we were members. My children were members of the Cretan dance group. The Cretan Association was founded in 1967, at the old church. We had our meetings there at the basement. It was the first [Greek] local association in Vancouver. Slowly, more associations were formed, and at one point we had thirty-two associations! And now we have three or four …

What other changes can you see in Vancouver and in the community?

What I see is, since we have this large metropolitan community of Vancouver—of course, there are two more Greek communities—we could have had more registered members. For some reason, people believe that you do not need to be a registered member of the Community. However, the Community has expenses, as we all know from our households. We should not think that the Community will be there. It is not a given thing. We have to keep it.

Do you have a special memory you want to mention?

The only thing I want to say is that in those olden days, when my children were young, we had zeal. We were eager to participate in Canadian celebrations. There was Canada Day, on July 1st. Then there was Greek Day, which the City gave to us on the last Sunday in June. Greek Day started in 1974. I remember the night [before Greek Day] and I want to say it. In one evening, I and two sisters—my koumbares—sat and sewed the three costumes which we wore the following day. Because the Cretan Association needed to show that we were “something” and we did that. It had not been around for long since 1967 and we had not bought any costumes. So we presented [on Greek Day]. In those days, despite our limited means, we prepared floats for the parade. We had a parade [on Greek Day]. It was not just selling food; we had floats, we had a parade, all the children were dancing. At the steps of the Art Gallery, they used to have a celebration for new Canadian citizens. At that place, there was a big square with steps and the new citizens were taking their citizenship oath there.

Were you invited?

And they were inviting us to bring the children dressed up in the local/national costumes. We couldn’t wait—both we and the children … To load them in the cars, all dressed up, and so on … with our flags. They danced. And I remember they would also offer cake.

To hear audio clips from Effie’s interview and other Hellenic Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Greg Rudloff

“It’s a Nice Festival”

Greg Rudloff was interviewed on June 14, 2017, at Vancouver Public Library’s Dunbar Branch as part of the Story City project.

Dunbar has Salmonberry Days, which runs through May every year and has been going for twenty-five years now. Just a lot of little community events that go on, that are organized by our core group of people. A couple of people in this neighbourhood, twenty-five years ago, were talking about how there wasn’t a lot of spirit in the neighbourhood. “What we need to do is have a festival for this.” So, these two people got together with a few of their friends and decided, “Well, let’s decide a time in May. We’ll just schedule the event and see who turns out.” So, it’s virtually all free. It’s kind of evolved over the years. Of course, people love it, and have for years. It’s a nice festival.

What’s the funnest part?

Well, every year, they bring out one of the old city buses from the transit museum—the city has a transit museum with all the old buses—and they take you on a tour somewhere. This year, they went out to Steveston, to the cannery. The old cannery. Another year they went to Westin Island to some of the farms out there. Every year it’s different. So, it’s just kind of like you load up. You have to get there early or you don’t get a seat. Because, the only number of seats here. It’s usually a sellout. These people go off for the day, and do a tour somewhere.

To hear audio clips from Greg’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Larry Wong

“A Community Within a Community”

Larry Wong was interviewed in 2015 as part of the Chinatown Stories project.

There was a movie theatre called Rex Theatre on Hastings, just off Carral Street. In fact, it’s near where the present day Army & Navy store is located. I used to go to the Rex Theatre practically every Saturday matinee. It was one of those beautifully designed and built theatres where you pay for your ticket at a box office, you go to the lobby, and you’re greeted by an usher. He’ll take you up the ramp, and when you get up to the top, it’s actually a mezzanine. And main theatre itself is sort of stadium-like, so it goes down, but you can go up to the mezzanine.

And I was always ushered to the upper left side of the theatre, which was fine, but I didn’t understand why he always took me up there, until one day I found out it was because it was Chinese-only, like I wasn’t allowed to sit anywhere else in the theatre. So, I didn’t realize that until many years later and I said, “Oh my God, no wonder!” But I’d gotten used to sitting in the upper left section of the theatre. But I never really contemplated that it was restricted. It was really strange. Anyway, that’s how it was in those days. There’s a hotel called the May Wah. But it changed name over the decades, I don’t know why. But it was a particular hotel intended for newly arrived immigrants from a certain part of China. In other words, it would be the same district where my father came from. So it was really meant for immigrants from that village or county. And, when they arrive, and if they don’t have any place to stay, they go to this hotel.

When I was young, because we were living in the back of a tailor shop, see, we didn’t have hot water. Because the store was a store. It wasn’t meant for people living in the back. So you don’t have hot water, you see? So, what we did for hot water was that we had to boil the water and he would put it on the stove and heat it up. And from there, we have water for making tea, because my father loved making tea first thing in the morning. And then, we have hot water for washing our face and so on, you know.

But we had no bathtub. But my father was very adamant that I would have a bath. And luckily, his close friend lived in this hotel called the May Wah. And he made an arrangement for him to pick me up every Sunday to take a Sunday bath. So the close friend, his name was Dun Sing. He would drag me —Well, not really drag me, but he would take me by the hand back to the hotel. I was about six or seven years old. And he had a single room. Anyway, at the end of the hallway was the washroom. But also, they had a bathroom.

And then so, he would take me down there, and I would undress. And of course, the bathtub was one of those deep ones with the funny looking legs. And so, he would just fill it up, and I’d go and take my Sunday bath. And that was funny. But, I think it was very typical of the immigrants living in Chinatown at that time. Especially for immigrants who were merchants, and they were living in the back of the store, or the family was living in the back of the store. I think they would have the similar arrangements.

There was three Chinese schools: one was the Chinese Freemason, the other one was Mon Keang, and then the other one was a Chinese public school, where I went; it was kitty-corner from Strathcona School on Pender and Jackson Avenue. It used to be an old Ukrainian church, and what the Chinese school did, it used the lower part of the church, so they had several classrooms and also a large area for recess and so on. It was good. I’ve forgotten how much my father paid, but there was a fee that you paid to the public school, and I think the rest of it was subsidized by the community.

See, the thing that we learned at the Chinese school wasn’t a certain language or poetry or grammar and all of that, the main thing was learning how to play ping-pong. But going to school was very good, because Strathcona—originally, I think—was one of the first or second elementary schools in Vancouver, and they claimed themselves as being the “school of many nations,” because when you go there, well, before World War II, there were a lot of Japanese students, but we also had the Ukrainians, because the Ukrainians had their church nearby, and then you had the Jewish people, because they had the Jewish Synagogue nearby. And then you had the Russians, because the Russian Orthodox, they had their church nearby as well. So, it was sort of multicultural because of that. And also there was a handful of black people living nearby. So there was a fair representation of practically everyone from Vancouver, but they happened to live in Strathcona and they happened to go to this school.

So, that was one of the wonderful things I learned when I did go to public school, because you learned to get along with one another. In fact, I remember in Grade 8, we did this wonderful play called The Highway Man, and there was this scene, it was sort of a Romeo-and-Juliet scene where the man is up on the balcony and he’s kissing this girl. Well, what was really astounding, this took place in 1951, ‘52, the young male student was Italian, in fact his name was Gino Santaga, and the young girl he was kissing was Arlene Lane, who happened to be black. It’s like, “Wow, this is the first interracial kiss I’ve ever seen.” And it was true, because you don’t see that often, let alone in the school play, and this was, like I said, 1951. But for the teachers that were doing it, they really didn’t think anything of it because, although we were from different backgrounds, we were all students, period. And that’s how they looked at us, just, we were students.

We learned a great lesson from that, we learned a great sense of tolerance and understanding. It was a wonderful school.

Within the community it was very self-supporting, and it was out of necessity, because, really, the Chinese community was shunned by the white population. So, in Chinatown you’ll find that they’ll have their own place to shop for food, business to run. They have their own lawyers, they have their own accountants, they have their own school. So really, it was a community within a community. It was very restrictive, because as I understand it, very few Chinese ventured outside of Chinatown, and part of it was because they weren’t that welcome once they got out of the Chinatown.

In fact, I heard that it was quite rare, even when I was growing up, that a few Chinese would actually venture out to Granville Street, because on Granville Street they had these movie theatres at that time. They were afraid of it, because, again, of the discrimination, they may not be allowed in the movie theatre, or whatever. My siblings didn’t like the idea of living in the village. Basically Chinatown was a village. Everyone knew one another, in fact, I have a friend of mine, his name Wayson Choy, you might have heard of him. We met when we were in kindergarten.

Anyway, he used to talk a lot about me to his mother. So, his mother was really curious, and she came down to the shop to introduce herself to my father, saying, “Oh, I’m the mother of Wayson.” And so, they had a long chat. But, she wanted to check out my family! I mean, this was really something, because Wayson and I were really good friends, and he talked a lot about me to his mother. It got her curiosity aroused, and so she went down to check it out.

I guess, just by talking with my parents, and knowing about me from Wayson, she knew that Wayson had a very good friend, and that his friend has good parents, and that was really valuable. That was a real consideration in family relationships. I don’t know if you see that anymore these days, but it was something of value, and something that you can trust. So, whether that survives today, I don’t know, but there it was.

To hear audio clips from Larry’s interview and other Chinatown Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Marion Man

“Finally They Recognize Their Root”

Marion Man was interviewed in on September 4, 2015, as part of the Chinatown Stories project.

I’ve worked in Chinatown since 1976. I arrived in ’76 and I got my job, first job. Finding a job was tough at that time—1976, right? I found a job just next door to this church on Pender Street called Chinese Library. It’s still there. That library was founded by a group of CBC, Canadian Chinese-born kids. They felt that there was a need to preserve some Chinese culture, Chinese books, so they started that library, all on voluntary basis.

And I accidently got a job there. I was doing a lot of volunteer jobs when I came here. There was no jobs. I volunteered for SUCCESS, which is just up there on Pender Street, and I volunteered for YWCA also just a few blocks up there. There was a lot of voluntary agencies here in Chinatown at that time. But most of the jobs, they call it contract worker, that means government will give you funding for only three months or six months. And then you know by the end of the term you have to reapply, reapply again. I was working in Chinatown doing volunteer everywhere and I saw this lineup in front of a BC Royal restaurant and I bump into a guy who happened to be working next door in the Chinese Library and he told me there might be a possibility to get a job there. And that’s how I got my very first job here. As a contract worker.

And my work was going around in this neighbourhood here, in this Strathcona neighbourhood, to this housing, low-cost housing, mostly occupied by Chinese seniors, they can read and they can write. They speak Toishan, their native language. Not even Cantonese. I had a hard time communicating with them. There was a lot of fun stories, you know, we just misunderstood each other. I had to help them to write letters back to China, to their relatives. A lot of people, especially men, they came here without families. And so, it was a pretty lonely life here. They need to write back to China or read the letters from China and they were just ecstatic when they got a letter from China, usually they don’t get it on a regular basis, maybe twice a year three times a year, I was helping them to read it and write back to their families. So that was my first job.

You mentioned that it was kind of a lonely life. Were there certain buildings or opportunities for socializing, or were there certain places where people went to fight that loneliness at that time?

They call it the clansmen association, they have those, but most of those are playing Majong or gambling. A lot of people, immigrants, they came here and got into two big problems: one is gambling and second is prostitute. It’s a very sad story. Because subsequently I became a social worker in Chinatown. And I was working for Greater Vancouver Homemaker Association, so I have to visit all these buildings. There were fifty buildings in Chinatown—as of now, still fifty buildings—low-cost housing, by BC government, by city, or by clansmen. So I would have to do assessment, like what kind of needs do they have, and we send homemakers or home support to their house to help with the seniors. I remember one of the worst case I had, in May Wah hostel. That building was so very very old, very very run down. At that time, downstairs was chicken meat store, okay? And next door was travel agent, I believe still there. And then the upstairs, you see so many rats, cockroaches, all over then place. And people living in that building have no kitchen. They have a common [one], in the hallway there, they have a stove. And they also have a communal bathroom. So very, very substandard living, living there. And mostly men there, too. One of the men, I remember, he was really, really—almost like having a life in hell. Like most immigrants, they will save all their money to send back to China for their families. Usually what they did, they buy a meal, let’s say buy a meal with rice on it, you know like, two doors away from the May Wah is Dollar Meat, they buy something, maybe they don’t buy it there, it’s too expensive. They buy somewhere else a meal and chop it into three times to eat it. For whole day. That means one meal for whole day. So their health condition is very poor. And this guy has also got some disease. He blame it on the prostitute, he says, “I got it from that lady.” His body got all this—what you call it—lumps, big lumps in his body, all over his back, all over his front, it’s just terrible. And he won’t go to hospital. So the nurse will come and try to put bandage on it or try to do some sort of hygienic cleaning. So that was the life they have, you know. For most of the immigrants in those days. They were working in Chinese restaurant or laundromat, that was their life, their work.

Chinatown used to be occupied by most of Chinese people here. Immigrants, you know, they had a tough life. They had some sad history, as well. Some have been discriminated, some of them never had a chance to be educated. So once they’re able to make some money or financially they have more affordability, they want to move out of Chinatown. They don’t want to remember. They don’t want to stay here as a ghetto. And so they move out. And second generation, too. I have so many CBC friends, they did not want to speak Chinese. I’m talking about forty years ago, they did not like to learn Chinese, but now they regret, they say, “I wish I can speak Chinese.” So those were the mentality, and that’s why people are moving out. And church are being closed down. And the church that survive here—some of them—are very, very old churches here, like the one on Gore and Pender. That’s over a hundred years old.

I think church was very, very important for the Chinese immigrants at that time. Because they were isolated, somehow. They did not have a lot of friends. And church is a place that they feel safe. They don’t feel that they’re segregated. So church was an important part of their lives, you know. And now, church still very important in this particular location, because the church is situated between Downtown East and Strathcona-Chinatown here. And both communities have a lot of marginal people. In Chinatown—this church is serving a lot of the seniors here. All the seniors are low income, and they are also very, very lonely. Still. It doesn’t matter, before or now, seniors are lonely by nature. Because the family, you know, in Canada, a lot of children, they don’t even live in Vancouver, let alone live with the parents. So they are living alone in this low-cost housing. I think they need the support. This church is trying to offer support to this marginal group of seniors here.

Also to try to welcome the newcomers here, too. Now the people coming to this church, not just Chinese people, also there’s a lot of Caucasian, new families coming in here, and so they also attend this church, as well. So they can serve the families and children and youth here. And on the other side there’s the Downtown East here, we have a lot of addicts and we have a lot of homeless people, and this church welcome them to come. We have a smaller church, they basically emphasize working with this group of people. So I think church plays a very important role in this location, in Chinatown location. For the reason that the capacity of the population and the different ethnic groups here. It’s very multicultural here in Chinatown, as you can see it, right?

Also, this church now is not like before. Before it’s a Catholic church, it was a Korean church before this, and now it’s a community church. That means we embrace everybody here. We don’t have any denominations. Now we have four churches working together here. We might have more. We like to see this church as a community centre. Who need to come to use it, they can use it. Even some social agencies, they have a need to use it, we have an open door for them to use it as well, too.

I was working with the marginal most the time as a social worker. Most of the people I serve, they are underprivileged, and they are somehow segregated from the mainstream. They never had the chance to mingle with the mainstream. So in that sense, there is some sort of segregation there. That’s why I understand why those second generation CBC, they don’t want to identify themselves as Chinese. I come to understand why they don’t want to learn Chinese. Because they want to be more identified as local people, as Canadian people. They don’t feel they’re Chinese people. They don’t want to feel that they are Chinese people. But now, I think things have changed a little bit. Thanks to this multiculturalism, the promotion of multiculturalism, people think: “You are who you are and you should be proud of who are. You should be proud of your root, and your root can contribute to this multiculturalism.” And so I think that’s been improved in my opinion.

I see some people moving back here. The third generation, they are moving back to Chinatown, some of them. Still not in a big wave. But I see some of them, which is a good sign. I think finally they recognize their root, and they are not ashamed of their past.

To hear audio clips from Marion’s interview and other Chinatown Stories participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Anna Terrana

“The Centre Became My Second Home”

Anna Terrana was interviewed on March 1, 2017, as part of the Story City project.

My name is Anna Terrana. Some of the things I’ve done: I’ve been the executive director of the Italian Cultural Centre Society, I was also the president for five years, and I was also a Member of Parliament.

Could you tell me a little about [coming to Canada]?

Well, I was very happy where I was. I’m from Torino, in Piemonte. I used to work with the Americans. I had a very good job, in fact. But I met the man of my dreams, I suppose, and we married. But he was a very unstable person, he wasn’t able to stay in the same place for a long time. And in fact he had just arrived … from Australia where he had lived for nine years. He was originally from Trieste in Italy. And we ended up getting married and he didn’t want to stay in Italy and here we are. Here I am.

We arrived in October 1966. And I was very sad. I didn’t want to be here. I wanted to be where I was … But somehow everything turned in a way that I could not say no. I just had to come. Even at the last minute, I was at the airport, and behind me there was the pilot of the plane, and the woman at the counter said that she could not let me come to Canada because I did not have a visa. I didn’t know I needed a visa, nobody ever told me anything. And so she said, “I cannot let you go.” Then the pilot said, “No, just stop it,” he said, “I’ll take this lady with me to Canada and if they don’t want her, I’ll bring her back.” Well, they wanted me. Here I am.

In ’75, [my husband] and I split, so I found myself alone with this child. Thank God I had a good job. I was the administrator of the BC Place Commissions. I had to look after this child, and I had nobody, no family support, no anything.

I started with Big Brothers, and the United Way, and I went on from there. And then I saw that they wanted to build a centre, the Consul of Italy … They told me “Why don’t you build a centre for the community? And the government will help you.” We started from there.

[I lived in] the same place in Burnaby for, how is it? Forty-six years. So I made up for the eight years that I had to move. Because my husband and I separated, so I stayed there. I stayed there because of David, my son. Because he needed to have some stability in life.

It was very difficult for me to do all the things then. But he was very supportive. He always was there when I needed him. And David, when he was growing up, then we had to run home, make supper, and go again to the meeting, take him to the meeting—poor David. The Centre became my second home. I was thinking of just leaving a bed there because I was there from nine o’clock in the morning ‘till eleven o’clock at night. Weekends, the same thing. People knew that I was there so they came by. They were fun times.

Did you put your son into language school?

David, no. David doesn’t even speak Italian, and you know I used to teach Italian. In Italy, I taught some Italian. And here, I started the ESL courses. The City of Vancouver had this project and again someone gave my name. This was 1969–1970. Peter Davis was in charge of this project from the City of Vancouver and then it involved was also the Federal Government and the United Church. And the idea was to bring, to have a bunch of us … for instance they started with the Italian and Chinese communities. Maggie Ip, you probably heard of her before: she has always been a very active Chinese person and she has also been a counsellor at City Hall. So she was in charge of the Chinese community and I was in charge of the Italian community.

The idea was to bring these people with their children. Because the women ended up staying at home and the men were out working. So they were working and learning English but the women had no chance to do that. So we got them out of the house with their children, and we taught them English. We started in September/October and we ended in June … it was six months altogether. These people in the end could speak English. Because they did have English in their ears and they needed some attention.

We were holding the classes at Saint Francis of Assisi because it was then the Italian church. So downstairs they have a small hall, and we had people looking after the children, and we had grandmothers. But I was teaching in the evening, so no grandmothers because they ended up going in the afternoon, but to this day occasionally I run into to someone and it’s, “Oh Anna!” One in particular, because he lives in Burnaby where I live. But usually I don’t even recognize them because so many years have gone by.

To hear audio clips from Anna’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Anna Zhao and Son

“There’s Lots of Good Social Support Here”

Anna Zhao and her son were interviewed May 24, 2017, as part of the Story City project.

First name is Anna. Last name is Zhao.

Okay. So you’ve been in Vancouver how long?

We moved in 2014, because I went to UBC for my Master. It was a pretty big move. We pretty much sold everything in China. Because his father passed away, so there’s two of us, we moved here, just us. So far, it’s an amazing place, living. I don’t regret about my decision moving here. Because compared to Beijing, people are nicer, more friendly, and more open. With cultural diversity too, you meet people from all walks of life and from every different countries. And that we’re all living here is pretty amazing. You don’t see that anywhere in the world, really. I think I got lots of support from the communities. I’m trying to get my permanent residency. I’m not really a permanent resident yet. But I got lots of support from, like he got a Big Brother. I don’t know if you’re familiar with that program. It’s like a charity or nonprofit program for kids, from eight to fifteen who need more male support, either single moms or widows, or even divorced people, if they don’t have enough hours with their fathers or their male figures. And they provide volunteers, they go out every week, they have to set up a role model for them, and basically, moms stay out of it. And it’s just them. So they have fun together. So luckily, we got a role model.

Anna’s son : There’s also a program called Big Sisters.

Yeah, that’s the opposite, for girls. There was a bit wait time, but luckily we got a really good one for him, since last May actually. So it’s been a year. I’m really happy with it. And also, I go to single mothers’ support group, sponsored by the YWCA. So there’s lots of good social support here.

To hear audio clips from Anna’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Greg Rudloff “It’s a Nice Festival”

Greg Rudloff was interviewed on June 14, 2017, at Vancouver Public Library’s Dunbar Branch as part of the Story City project.

Dunbar has Salmonberry Days, which runs through May every year and has been going for twenty-five years now. Just a lot of little community events that go on, that are organized by our core group of people. A couple of people in this neighbourhood, twenty-five years ago, were talking about how there wasn’t a lot of spirit in the neighbourhood. “What we need to do is have a festival for this.” So, these two people got together with a few of their friends and decided, “Well, let’s decide a time in May. We’ll just schedule the event and see who turns out.” So, it’s virtually all free. It’s kind of evolved over the years. Of course, people love it, and have for years. It’s a nice festival.

What’s the funnest part?

Well, every year, they bring out one of the old city buses from the transit museum—the city has a transit museum with all the old buses—and they take you on a tour somewhere. This year, they went out to Steveston, to the cannery. The old cannery. Another year they went to Westin Island to some of the farms out there. Every year it’s different. So, it’s just kind of like you load up. You have to get there early or you don’t get a seat. Because, the only number of seats here. It’s usually a sellout. These people go off for the day, and do a tour somewhere.

To hear audio clips from Greg’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.

Julia Lane “People See You When You’re Flustered

Julia Lane was interviewed on August 4, 2017, at Mount Pleasant Community Centre, as part of the Story City project.

I came into the library. I had my stroller, I had like way too much stuff with me, as I usually do. So I had too much stuff, and I had a library fine, which never happens because I’m very fastidious about not having library fines. I was flustered, and I was wanting to pay my library fine. It wasn’t a lot of money, it was like $2, but I didn’t have any cash, I was trying to find cash, couldn’t find any cash. “So can I just pay you this with my debit card? I know it’s dumb, it’s only $2.” The librarian would say, “It’s okay, settle down, you’re fine.” And then some person came up behind me and he was like, “I’ll pay it for you, it’s fine,” and I was like, “No, no, I can pay it. It’s not like I don’t have the money.” He’s like, “No, you look like you’re having a rough day.” I said, “I’m actually fine, I’m not upset. I just have too many things and I’m flustered.” And so he paid the library fine for me after much protestation on my part, and he gave my son Felix five bucks, and I was like, “We really don’t need to take your money, sir. Like thank you, we’re fine.” And he was like, “No, no, I want him to have it, it’s his now.” That was an interesting moment where I was like, Wow, I must have come off very needy in this particular instance. But I just left feeling very like supported by the community here, feeling like, okay people see you when you’re flustered and might want to help out, so that was really nice.

To hear audio clips from Julia’s interview and other Story City participants, please explore the full collection at thisvancouver.vpl.ca.